All right. Hello everyone. It's
September 4th, aka 3 to the 2 power, 2
to the 2 power. Um 2025 is a square two
and we're in chapter 7.
So there's a few new learning resources
and uh code examples that I have queued
up.
or we could take a big picture look at
chapter 7. But let's just begin. If
there's any section of the chapter or of
anything that that comes to mind for
people,
let's just start there.
So it could be a o overall remark on
chapter 7 or its position in the book.
um
could be some section
or or a question or an idea about about
what chapter 7's doing or or what it's
up to.
Or I can give a sort of summary remark
on what chapter 7 is is doing um and
start to share some of these more recent
resources too. But first, just anyone
who has a comment or question they want
to give can go for it or type it in the
chat and I'll watch.
Okay. Okay. Let's just zoom into a quick
overview, but raise your hand or or
write in the chat if if anyone has a
question. So again, the first half of
the book is the epistemic and background
content. The second half of the book is
intended to be more like a workbook or a
guide book getting us towards building
specific generative models. Chapter 1
and 10, they're kind of like the book
ends. That's the big picture and the
theory review. Two and three give us the
low and the high road to get to the
generative models of active inference.
And then five explores mammal
neurobiology which is a really
wellstudied system complex one but well
studied. Then we head into the the back
stretch. Chapter six is the recipe for
designing active inference models. So
those are kind of the ingredients and
the processes that any given generative
model, any given agent in environment
model is going to have to address. So
whether it's a rat in a T-mase or it's a
motor circuit connected to an arm
actuator, those are the kinds of
questions that any given model is going
to have to be addressing. Then we get
into 789. So that's kind of the stretch
that we're heading into right now. Seven
and 8 go into more detail into the
discrete time in seven and continuous
time models in 8. That's kind of like a
uh a little bit of a mitosis event
relative to figure 4.3.
So figure 4.3,
we have these on the top discrete time
and on the bottom continuous time. We
can talk more about their similarities
and differences, but they're clearly
laid out in figure 4.3 to show their
structural similarity.
And then chapter 7 and 8 kind of go into
more detail about some features of
discrete and continuous time models. And
then chapter 9 talks about well what if
we want to connect models to empirical
data whether we want uh previous to
chapter 9 it's more about just kind of
instantiating a model and then
generating synthetic data in chapter 9
the models get inverted where we have a
situation that has already yielded data
like we already have choice behavior
from the mouse in the maze and now we're
going to go back to parameterize
some factor in the cognitive model.
That's the big picture on the whole
book. And seven is going to focus on the
top figure here.
Seven is going to build towards this
model. So, here's where
Oh, yes. Figure 4.3
page 70 in the book. Yeah. Or or or or
just in the KOD as well.
So again, chapter 4 where we're actually
at that center point between the low and
the high road.
Chapter 2 coming up from the low road.
Chapter 3 coming down from the high
road. Chapter four in active inference
city. And then we meet kind of the two
types of entities there discrete and
continuous time.
Those get revisited in chapter
7 and 8. So that's where we are uh
today.
Um when it comes to chapter 7,
well, I'll just share a few. Um
this I I have done this over the last
several days. Made this repo called
start
and did a short stream on it. This repo
does a few things. First, it it hosts a
bunch of links. Then it has a generative
AI component to generate custom
curriculum. So like for a given entity
or audience, it will write a custom
introductory curriculum. Not perfect,
but a nice fun starting point. And then
also it clones
other repositories of applications. So
like I've made a fork then of pmdp
which kind of builds us up to what we
get to in chapter 7. So just know that
if we want to look at more of a code
implementation of anything that we're
about to go over, we can pop over to uh
look at the code.
Okay. So
any comments or questions just on that
sort of general situating of what
chapter 7 is is doing
Okay.
So, um
there's a lot to say about
categoricalness
and continuousness.
And I'll start with one of on one of the
the branches of PIMDP
with this image of just a few um
features of distributions.
So
>> hey Daniel, I'm still just seeing your
the active inference textbook. Are you
sharing your screen?
>> Let me try again.
Do you see this distributions?
Okay. All right.
So, um, two main distribution types that
we're going to be talking a lot about
are discrete distributions or the
categorical distribution and then
continuous distributions of which one
type is a Gaussian or a normal. So
categorical is where there are discrete
differing options. So these are state
spaces. This could be like temperature.
We could be parsing up temperature into
like it's cold, medium, hot, and there's
just three options for temperature. Or
we could have temperature be like a
continuous variable
um in a in a normal distribution. and
parameters have different values that
characterize their shape.
Um,
chapter 7 and 8
are dealing with whether time is dealt
with in a discrete or continuous
fashion.
Whether time is dealt with in continuous
or discrete fashion, the state space
could also be continuous or discrete.
So, but time is kind of a special
variable because of uh how it influences
change in the dynamics of the model. And
this is a common distinction that comes
up in a lot of other modeling too. Um
okay,
so
this chapter is going to focus on
categorical variables in discrete time.
So this is kind of the most categorical
discrete possible quadrants where we're
dealing with discrete clicks of time.
Like time is just going to happen in
these steps rather than being like a
flow. And then the state spaces of the
variables are also going to be these
categorically different outcomes.
There's going to be a sequence of
examples
which again have have um some light code
presented in the appendix of the book in
mat lab or you can look at the pmdp code
um and it's going to build towards that
figure 4.3 or as as it will come to be
seen figure 7.3 is just that the top
half of figure 4.3. three, we're going
to get to this shape which we will um
come to know and love
in a stepbystep fashion.
Any any
comments or questions here?
Okay.
So the the first
>> Sorry, can I ask a quick question?
>> Yeah.
>> Um
tell me really quickly how to think
about
a discretet state space, you know,
moving from one state to another state.
And each of those discrete states is
composed of a dynamic flow.
Tell me real quick how to think about
Yeah. Okay. So, let's in the discrete
situation, it's like we're on a
chessboard, like we're in a location
that's discreetly different. Whereas the
continuous case is like a field, like
you have a GPS coordinate. So, it's
still it still could be the same grid,
but you're going to be continuously
different. Then if you wanted to have a
situation where there was at a higher
level a discrete choice
and then like within each cell you have
a GPS field.
So then you can say you know I'm in cell
A2
at this higher discrete level and then
within A2 I'm at 77.44.
So that could be done with a nested
model or there could be other ways but
that's just sort of one one way to do
it.
Okay. So we have okay where where we're
going is top half of figure 4.3
this partially observable marov decision
process which is kind of like our
this is going to be kind of like our
Drosophila our fruitfly that we're going
to work to in terms of summarizing
the core cognitive features of
perception and action selection.
So the first example
is just the downstairs. So this part is
just the part that looks kind of like a
hair comb or like a downward-facing
letter E with a little handle.
And what's happening here is there's a
S. So a true latent state. This could be
like the temperature in the room. And
then at every latent state moment, every
time subscript the current moment
subscript towel
or the past or the present or the past
or the future with a negative 1 or plus
one, it emits an observation
through A.
So latent state is changing through time
according to this B transition matrix.
Every time step an observation is
emitted like a thermometer reading is
emitted from the latent state. And then
we have D which is the initial prior on
the latent state just to kick the chain
off. But D is just used in the first
time step and then for all later time
steps like
TA minus one S S subt minus one plays
the role of D to S subt. Okay,
so this is just there's no action in
this model yet. There's just the
unfolding
deterministic or probabilistic time
evolution unfolding of this chain of
S's. And then you also have a series of
observations,
but the observations aren't like linked
to each other. they're only linked back
to this main spine which is the time
evolution of like the temperature in the
room. But you do also have this sequence
of thermometer readings. So this is a um
hidden marov model because we have a
hidden variable or latent variable s
which is the one that's actually with a
marovian property with this transition
matrix but we get an observable at every
time step. Um
the example that that they use for this
type of model is a music listening
model.
So it's like there's a sequence of
notes, there's a true sequence of notes,
and then there's a heard sequence of
notes and then there's a transition
matrix B which governs which notes are
actually changing like in the score and
then there are there are observations
and beliefs which could be concordant or
disincent with how they are observed.
Okay. So, it's just a pure perception
example.
It's basically just covering
um those core
downstairs ideas.
How do you kick off the latent state
with an initial prior? How do latent
states evolve through time with a
transition matrix that gives it a
marovian property?
How do latent states at each time emit
an observation
through the A matrix?
And then I'll just add the sort of
chapter 9esque idea is what if we run
that a matrix backwards and instead of
thinking about the latent state emitting
a likely observation,
we think about just having an
observation and then pushing it back
through a the other way and asking okay
given that observation what is the
latent state app to be?
Okay. So any
just you know random comments or any
questions on this perceptual
downstairs part of the discrete time
model.
Last uh comment you made it has to do
with uh the inversion. So that would be
how you would get to your like your
posterior or your recognition density.
Exactly. That's like the so-called tale
of two densities,
>> right?
>> Yeah. Is you can start from um the
temperature of the room. Like let's just
say this is our a matrix. So the 110th
it it's written this way just so that
there's integers there. But this could
also be like 7.1.1
instead of this 110. Like the one10th
distributes through the whole matrix.
Um, so we could either um start with a
real room temperature
and then say what is it? Let's just say
it's um cold, cool, warm, hot.
So we could say we're going to be
simulating this room that is cold. What
temperature readings are we likely to
get? Was it 70% likely that it's going
to be cold, 10% likely that it's cool?
And so on. Or we could run it the other
way and say we got this observation of
it being very hot on the thermometer.
It's 70% likely that the room is in that
state.
So that's the the tail two densities or
the generative density which is going
from the latent state to the observation
that's like generative AI or from the
observation going back to a latent state
estimate.
Okay,
this this chapter comes at comes out one
fast because that was the downstairs
part. So now that's going to stay
exactly the same. And now all that is
added to get to a full active inference
perception action joint distribution
is these two variables up here.
So now instead of B just being a single
matrix that goes from from to to like
the transition matrix of from
sunny and cloudy days. Like it could
just be that they stay the same 90% of
the time and they change 10% of the
time. So it's like 0.9.1.9
a little square. just each time step you
just apply that transition matrix and
you end up staying in the current
weather pattern 90% of the time.
Now what's going to happen is there's a
action selection variable or policy
variable pi and now there's going to now
B is going to grow from being just a
square matrix into being a tensor which
is kind of like a collection of index
cards. It could just be two index cards
but they're all the same shape index
card. And then what action selection is,
it's like rifling through the index card
file cabinet and saying which index card
am I going to play to transition the
latent state.
So that is what action selection comes
down to. Which transition matrix should
I apply
to the latent state time evolution?
That's what pi does.
And then G is the expected free energy
which is going to say how should I
update how I select which index card to
play.
So we have pi which is initially
a prior on which action we're going to
play
and then you could just draw randomly
from that
uh policy prior or you could update the
policy prior into a policy posterior
using this expected free energybased
procedure. which we'll talk more about
so that you sample actions
proportionally with their pragmatic and
epistemic value.
So that's kind of the key idea of the
active inference components
because on the downstairs we can do the
basian updating the perceptual sense
making
all of that is happening with a
variational free energy bounding
surprise of observations
um real-time inference even learning
all those kinds of features don't
require action selection at all
and we get to full active inference when
we're thinking about what the agent is
doing as this joint distribution
where it's able to first I mean where
it's able to jointly
update its beliefs about latent states
and update its beliefs about actions
Daniel.
Um
uh so I I understand the updating of the
actions, but is it possible for those
for there to be a like one of the index
cards so to speak being uh gen being
generative in the sense of I don't know
it could be like random
>> um
a random matrix could still have a lot
of structure.
So, um, but yeah, like the, uh,
one of the B, one of the B matrix slices
could be like a uniform distribution
like just kind of grayed out or just
sort of like SC depending on the
situation like we can look at it in the
T-mas and maybe see where that makes
sense or not.
But yeah, the the the slices of B
represent beliefs about the causal
consequences of selected actions.
Now, there's kind of two layers of of of
uh of challenge in the modeling there,
which is summarized a little bit in
figure 9.1. So, here's that figure 4.3,
figure 7.3. This is the rat and the
teenage that we're about to look at
here.
Were the experimentter in the lab making
the cognitive model of the rat? And
there's these kind of two uh two veils
of unknowing. First, the rat could have
a facious understanding of its actual
situation.
Second, we could have a facious model or
a useless model of the rat.
So the situation that that sort of
seems to check all the boxes would be
like we're we are properly calibrating a
model
to an agent that is skillfully engaging
with the niche.
That's kind of the paradigmatic case
where we have a useful cognitive map of
an agent that has a useful cognitive
map.
But
the tools on our workbench allow us also
to make the fantastical and the facious
and the pedagogical models as well. So
just by virtue of cobbling a model
together using these components, it
doesn't mean it fits the world well
for an agent to have and it doesn't mean
that we're going to fit the bird well
just by building it. But but these are
the components that help us get to those
places.
So like so and that the reason why I
brought that up in response to like
could there be kind of a random action?
So it's like
the agent environment question is like
does the agent have an action it thinks
it can select that would lead to a
scrambling of the latent states in the
environment. I mean maybe it's a reset
button on the slot machine or something.
So there could be a situation where that
totally applies or maybe that could be
nonsensical
and then it would be
would we be right in identifying that be
for that organism.
Um okay
here um in the
>> ask a quick question
>> uh please
>> who who is the policy known to
um does the agent Yeah I guess that's my
question
>> yes great question it's a belief that
the agent has about what it is apt to
do.
We don't need to take it into like the
phenomenological. So it isn't
necessarily that like it rises to a
conscious awareness. It doesn't need to
take on a sort of experiential baggage.
We could talk about the policy of a
bacteria to either run or tumble. We say
it's 80% of the time it runs, 20% of the
time it tumbles and it updates or it
does action selection based on that. So
we that doesn't need to take on the
baggage like it's experiencing or having
like a self-awareness of knowing run and
tumble. But when we're doing this kind
of modeling, it's like all of these
variables
are on board the agents.
They're all part of
>> you could take that on. Is that right?
think that you could map that sort of in
a hierarchical fashion if you will that
there is a a conscious awareness of pol
discrete policy awareness if you want to
call it that way.
>> Yes.
>> Fair. Exactly. Yes. So, so at just at
the first base level, all of the
variables here, A, B, C, D, E, you know,
F and G, basically pi, those are the
joint distributions. That's the packet,
that's the Python class that you need to
describe the agents. Then you could have
a hierarchical model where it's like
okay we're going to have a kind of
supervening model or supervisory or a
hierarchical model that's looking at pi
as an observation coming up a hierarchy
and that's where people start to get
into like um introspection
and metacognition as awareness
is like if a variable could be observed.
I mean, observing an internal variable
is metacognition.
And then mental action is well, what if
you what if that was a two-way street
and observations of internal variables
were arising and then mental action or
attention or control were a descending
policy of metacognitive variables on
first order cognitive variables.
Okay. Um, could I I have a question
about terminology?
Uh,
I've I've come to interpret belief
as
uh what has been experienced
which is is related to why I asked my
question.
You know in terms of creativity we often
think of that again on a very high level
as making
new connections
between existing
uh connections. Uh but again the
interpretation of belief is
like what exists or what has been
experienced.
Which is why I asked the question can it
be can the belief be something
completely newly just
um generated? I guess in a way you got
at that at the random
uh instantiation but
again the terminology belief or or or
prior it's it's something that's been
experienced. It's like the default.
Yeah. I I think there's a lot of pieces
there.
The prior which is to say before the
next observation
is like
the calibration of the sensor before the
next observation comes in. And then when
it comes to novelty
belief updating is going to stay within
the rails. Like if it's a distribution
that varies between zero and one you're
going to move around within that zero to
one space. And then there's this kind of
like categorical novelty with like what
if you what if the structure of the
belief changes
and that's kind of approached in
structure learning
where the actual like type of the
variable can change or a new node could
appear or connect connections
like components could change in the
graphical model
which opens up like a a very massively
combinatorial brick creative novelty.
Whereas this is more like it's kind of
like the plane is already built. It's in
flight and like each of the flaps could
be between zero and one. The engine can
go to but like we're not going to be
adding new flaps or taking flaps off.
So it's kind of like on the rails within
the support. That's that's the the term
that comes up a little earlier in the
book is support which is basically the X
range that a statistical distribution
covers.
So those that's like the state of play
for a given variable.
Okay.
So we got to the kind of key 7.3
which is this downstairs sensemaking
component
now with a policy selection variable
that's picking which slice of B is going
to be used in the causal unfolding.
Um, so instead of just here's the here's
the um hot and cold that stays the same
temperature 90% of the time and it flips
10% of the time. That's just a single
2x2 matrix. Now we have turn on the air
conditioner, do nothing, turn on the
heater and the air conditioner biases
the temperature down and the heater
biases it up and do nothing keeps it,
you know, one and keeps it the same or
you could have it it randomizes the the
temperature, whatever. And then there's
a procedure with expected free energy
for how you update your policy prior
into a policy posterior.
So it's the same kind of general basian
concept. This is why it is literally
active inference because it's policy and
action selection as an inference problem
to update your policy prior belief which
is what what I was apt to do before I
updated beliefs about how it's apt to
be.
Then after I've updated how it's apt to
be,
what am I apt to do
given
what information I might receive from
actions which is the epistemic value and
how action might orient with my
preferred observations.
There's calibration to be done to
actually finesse the exploit explore
there.
The special case is the purely
pragmatic.
This is the special cases that are
described in figure 26.
Here's expected free energy pragmatic
value and epistemic value. So it's the
other order. But here is epistemic is
the first term, pragmatic is the second
term. Here's the other way around. Just
to be clear, if you only have pragmatic
value,
>> if you're showing the 2.6, we're not
seeing it.
>> Oh, it's kind it's like
I updated Pop OS.
Okay. 26.
If you only have the pragmatic value
term,
you have pragmatic value or utility
maximization
which is basically reinforcement
learning. You have a a value function.
You have a utility function and then
actions are selected that either you
pick the best action or you draw from
the posterior probability of actions
proportionate to their expected utility
return.
Conversely, if you the other special
case of expected free energy is if you
say actually I equally prefer all
outcomes and that connects to that kind
of like equinimity type um phenomenology
and you only have epistemic value.
Epistemic value maximization leads to a
noveltybased search where actions are
selected solely upon their expected
information gain.
And then there's this finessing of
how much and in what ways and with what
switching strategy
of which level of the model etc etc etc.
Do you want to pursue pragmatic and/or
epistemic ends?
And if the situation is such that
the policies that are pragmatic are also
yielding epistemic value,
then there's no conflict. So it doesn't
really matter. But that finessing comes
into play when there are policies that
have where those vectors are not
completely aligned. And in most
situations you can imagine that they're
probably not. But you can design a
situation where they completely are. So
in the general case there there's
there's no there's not too much to say
just that you could you could imagine
those are like the state spaces
of of different models and different
information possibilities.
Now now do you see the textbook again?
Okay. Okay.
But what G does is it takes in the
policy prior pi.
It scores each of the policies according
to those two attributes.
We can go into more detail with what the
variables are if people want, but it
scores policies according to that. Um,
and then it reweights the policies
likelihood of being selected based upon
their score on that
G.
And then with your action posterior,
your reweed policy, you know what I'm
apt to do now, now that I know what I
know now, actions are either you take
the best scoring policy or you sample
from that
distribution of policies.
So that's the upstairs action selection
process.
So that's how the whole continuum from
epistemic novelty oriented behavior
novelty search
on through purely reinforcement reward
pragmatic utility that end of the pool
and modulations in between
are treated as part of this unified
action inference problem.
which gets composed onto a sensemaking
perception problem
without without the negative connotation
of problem or puzzle.
So that we have this downstairs
sensemaking,
upstairs action selection
that represent those two fundamental
inbound perceptual and then outbound
action emmitting aspects of things.
7.456 456
goes into more detail on the rat in a
T-mase
and uh
PMDP has a great example of a T-mas
and I I've I've made some additional uh
code methods
if to to look through.
7.4 4
goes a little deeper into epistemic
value
in terms of giving a few different ways
to to really zoom in on what what's
happening with um so the rat basically
here's its options. It starts in the
starting position. There's only four
positions in this whole scenario.
There's the starting position. Then
there's two ends of the maze.
one of them has a preferred sensation
like sugar and the other has nothing or
a dispferred sensation. Um you know so
people have done the teams in the sort
of reward seeking or in the uh
punishment aversion setting or both and
then the bottom position is a Q. So
basically the rat can go to any of to
make three choices. It could either go
to the left, go to the right or but it
doesn't know which one has the preferred
observation.
What it can do is it can go to the Q
which it has already used associative
learning in this situation to associate
okay if it's an L that means that the
good stuff is on the left.
So, it's like there's there's, you know,
there's two slot machines up ahead. One
of them is a high yield, one of them is
low yield, but I'm not exactly sure
which one is high and low yield. So, I
could just jump the gun and pick one or
the other.
Or I could ask this person who I believe
is going to be a source of uncertainty
reduction onto and then I'll go to which
one I think is better. So like that kind
of micro decision
which is a situation where it's like and
that kind of relates to like time
preference and and delayed gratification
in a sense. It's like if it were $10 and
$1 between the two slot machines,
but it's like but if I go to the queue,
maybe the queue costs money to go to or
may at the very least it's a time delay.
So, how do we model that situation where
information gain
is being traded off either temporally or
in terms of uh some kind of currency
with the possibility of rewards
7.1 is a little bit box 7.1
is A bit of a more background concept
about about um
entropy of distributions
just where when it's uh between
uh uh whether it's the inverse
temperature or the temperature of course
sets up whether it's going to be a
higher or a lower value. But there's a
knob that you can turn between something
being flattened
or being sharpened. It's kind of like
the gain on a distribution.
Uh 7.9
is just is a citation to dig into more.
It's not really presented with the
equations here. Um where there's four
locations. So it's actually in that way
quite similar to the T-mase because
there's also four locations in the
T-mase but here it's an eye cade
visual foraging task.
So the visual set I mean and this is
like one of the amazing truth drops of
the predictive mind which is that under
healthy vision we have color and clarity
in our whole visual field. Even though
color and clarity is actually only a
very small fraction at the center of our
vision, it's just like one of the most
most like mic drop. Like that's why
we're perceiving belief,
not processing inbound retinal photons.
The retinal photons are just fine-tuning
the generative model of what we believe
to have color and clarity,
even if we weren't looking at it.
So the visual foraging is a really
interesting example
for that. Then 7.5
uh goes into a little bit about how
learning can happen.
So here we have that same
seeing. Yes. See with a mind.
Here we have the same downstairs
hair comb. Here's D SS SS O
and the same kind of upstairs
action selection but there's some other
variables added. We can talk more about
it but that it relates to how each
variable in the base POMDP.
You could either just take it as fixed
or you could take each of those
variables like the A or the B or the D
as drawn from a hyper prior
distribution.
So it' be like in like if it were rainy
or sunny, you could say D is 0.5. It's
just 50/50 just that. Or you could say
actually my prior on the weather is 0.5
plus or minus.2.
So then across trials it'd be like okay
now I draw and it's 6040. Now I draw and
it's 40 60 and then it's 5545.
So then across many many trials you
would end up getting this normal
distribution
around 5050 but it wouldn't exactly
always be 50/50. So that's like the idea
of using Okay, this one Mark.
Yeah. Yeah. So here's here's the D that
we were working with before like 50/50
sunny cloudy
but it
may be drawn from another distribution
that could be like
so exact details are going to depend on
what shape the distributions are
but basically you can se you could have
instead of just like the 50/50 is like a
spike
and that itself could be a distribution
or like the preference values it you
know it could be I I prefer the le
prefer the sugar versus the nothing five
to one you say or I prefer it 5:1 plus
or minus one so then on the next trial
it could be 6 and.5 or something like
that.
So that's what a hyper prior is is it it
it like the bucks stops somewhere. There
is a level of the model where you just
say okay it's just
this is just the variable
but you can always in basian statistics
add another variable
which that
um one below it is sampled from.
So it seems to be bypassing that sort of
expected free energy.
I guess that's where I'm kind of getting
hung up here. It's having it's exerting
its own influence
>> and so it's sort of like the given.
Am I I don't know if I'm saying making
sense there.
Um
it's elaborating on the previous POMDP.
It's giving it the possibility of
learning of like multi-trial learning.
It doesn't really bypass. It's just in a
separate it's like this is kind of our
city.
So, and the edges are the information
flows.
So it's like again if it's 50/50 prior
on the weather, we could have a whole
causal model
that leads us to come to believe that in
this situation it's it's 8515
for the weather and then that would just
be used as the prior on S and then
everything else could go down the road
exactly the same.
So a lot of times the Marov blanket is
talked about as if it were the the one
that is partitioning the agent from the
world and that is an important blanket
to consider. But also just more
generically and uh less um or more
philosophically spicy depending on how
you think about it. Any intervening
variable blankets off any other
variables
like the influence of D
on S subt only is acting through S to
minus one
or the influence of this A learning
variable little A on O you know on the
relationship between S and O is only
acting through here. So you can add
whole branches
that are actually marov blanketed off
just because of of topological
partitioning.
So that kind of speaks to the
composability of the model is there's
different ways to swap out components
like a a matrix can get get very large
and in those situations that whole
component can get swapped out with a
neural network.
So, we're kind of learning the
matrix-based formulation,
which is the kind of
simplest, most analytically well-
definfined, most interpretable, most
index card, kind of back of the sheet.
But if the matrix were 10,000 by 10,000,
there could be a situation where you
just swap it out with a with a neural
network.
Um,
D could be its own neural network for
that matter.
>> Yeah. Sort of making a synaptic
connection to
>> an existing.
>> Okay.
>> Yeah. Like like so let's say the S is
going to be whether it's cloudy or
sunny. So it's just it's just going to
be give us, you know, 8020. But we could
to kick off the chain, we could um
download all the weather reports um
download all this data, send it to an
LLM and then say LLM
returning only two numbers that sum to
one. What is the probability that you
believe it's raining? And it will chug
chug chug chug chug and then come back
0.9.1.
So that would be like the LLM playing
the functional role of D emitting the
shape of the variable that we need to
kick off this whole chain.
But we're just going to write D as.9
in this kind of pure minimal matrix
form.
But like these are the kinds of of uh
debates that people have which was like
well if we replace every variable with a
neural network like is it still active
inference
or does it have to be just this kind of
matrix form like analytically closed
um style
7.2 two talks a little bit about this
idea of conjugate priors
which is basically what does little D
have to look like so that big D
is the shape that we need.
So that's a little bit about learning
and like that comes into this learning
by counting idea. So it's like that 0.5
we can think about it. It has like a
sort of parent distribution that's like
1 one and then 1 one goes to 0.5 and
then we see a sunny day. Now it's 2:1.
Now D goes to 2/3 1/3 and then we see
now it's 3 1 and then we update D to
75.25. So that's what the conjugate
distribution does in the learning by
counting situation
is it just runs a tally
and then it uses the ratio of the tally
as the prior for the next. And that's
also related to like the earn example
which is like you reach into an earn and
you pull out a ball. It's blue. Okay. So
now you believe that it's 100% blue in
the earn.
Then you pull out a purple one. Now you
believe it's 50% blue, 50% purple. Now
you pull out a second blue one. Now it's
2/3 blue, 1/3 purple. And you keep on
drawing.
And then you could come to a sort of um
understanding of when you were
asmmptoically sampling.
So learning by counting
example with a citation
structure learning just sort of alluded
to but that's this idea that basian
graphs that have different structural
features can be compared in terms of of
their uh their posterior evidence.
And then this hierarchical modeling
idea,
another example involving uh
uh multiple time scales and that's the
chapter.
So, it's kind of this one's kind of like
a roller coaster because it sets up the
two
real main dishes
with that downstairs sensemaking.
The upstairs action selection
goes in deep to the teammates with the
rat,
highlights the epistemic value
information seeking component.
And then the second half of the chapter
kind of like really quickly runs through
several related concepts and cites
several other papers that deploy
discrete models in different cases.
Any sort of closing ideas or
questions on seven.
Yeah, there's a lot of levels of
learning and like each of these
citations could be
investigated and you know modified.
>> Yeah, I'd like to echo uh Mark's
sentiment. Uh Daniel, you do such a
great job of of uh keeping focused on
the big picture while explaining the
individual parts. I just want to make
the comment that I've gone over this and
over this so many times and in trying to
conceptualize it and it's uh it's it's
so helpful to revisit and revisit and
revisit.
>> Thank you. Yes, it is. It there it is.
It is always surprising
the the textbook and and other materials
like there's just so much to revisit.
It's ridiculous.
Okay.
All right.
Thank you everyone. See you next time.